Guide to the George Bancroft papers, 1811-1901.
Bancroft, George papers, 1811-1901.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
George Bancroft papers, 1811-1901.
1262
George, Bancroft 1800-1891.
7 linear ft.
Correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Family and personal papers include correspondence of George Bancroft.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Historian, diplomat. Bancroft was a founder of Round Hill School, Northampton, Massachusetts, in 1823; served as U.S. Secretary of the Navy, 1845-1846; established the U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland, in 1845; served as U.S. minister to Great Britain, 1846-1849; to Prussia, 1867-1871; and to the German Empire, 1871-1874.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Family and personal papers include correspondence between George Bancroft and his first wife, Sarah Dwight (d.1837), his second wife, Elizabeth Davis Bliss, his father, Aaron Bancroft, his sister, Eliza Bancroft Davis, her husband John Davis, Governor of Massachusetts, his sister, Lucretia Bancroft Farnum, his two sons, George Bancroft, Jr., and John Chandler Bancroft during their school days and their travels abroad; other family letters are from other sisters and brothers, members of the Dwight family, Bancroft's two stepsons, Alexander and William Bliss, nieces, nephews, and other relatives; early deeds, other legal documents, papers pertaining to the settlement of various estates, and considerable genealogical material. Business and professional correspondence includes letters describing his involvement in Dwight family business interests, his stock holdings, and his work for the Bank of Michigan and other private banking ventures; letters and contracts with Little, Brown & Company detail his publication problems; and correspondence with his brokers and with his sons documents his later financial affairs, especially the income from his writings. There are some rough notes for his books and notes from personal interviews with Louis Philippe and Bismark. His political and diplomatic interests are documented by correspondence describing life in Washington, D.C., his career as Collector of the Port of Boston, and his advent as a cabinet official under Polk, as well as the Civil War and Reconstruction.
Correspondence documents his appointments as Minister to Great Britain in 1849 and Minister to Berlin, 1849-1867. There is also a series of letters to his wife in 1847 discussing French politics in detail as well as his reaction to French historians and philosophers. In addition, the collection contains a large number of autographed letters from persons prominent in public affairs and the literary world in Europe and America, 1817-1886; albums of photographs of the German royal family and others; bronze plaque honoring Bancroft; 90th birthday scrapbook; guest book, 1894-1899; and two letters, 1941, to Wilder D. Bancroft from the U.S. Navy regarding the launching of a ship named for George Bancroft. Included is correspondence by or about Ann Bancroft, Mary Bancroft, Sarah Bancroft, Thomas Bancroft, Alexander Bliss, William Bliss, T. Hartley Crawford, Jonathan Dwight, Jane Putnam Bancroft Gherardi, D. Goodwin, William Murphy, Henry Schoolcraft, Charles C. Trowbridge, Baxter Witter, and Levi Woodbury.
Also included is a letter to Bancroft from British statesman John Bright, dated March 29, 1862, which discusses in detail the reaction of the British public to the American Civil War.
Also, appointment of collector of customs for Boston, signed by Martin Van Buren, 1838.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bancroft, George,1800-1891.; Bancroft family.; Bancroft, Aaron, 1755-1839.; Bancroft, Ann.; Bancroft, Elizabeth Davis, 1803-1886.; Bancroft, George, Jr.; Bancroft, John Chandler.; Bancroft, Mary.; Bancroft, Sarah Dwight.; Bancroft, Thomas.; Bismarck, Otto, Furst von, 1815-1898.; Bliss, Alexander, 1792-1827.; Bliss, William Davis, 1826-1886.; Crawford, T. Hartley.; Davis, Eliza Bancroft.; Davis, John, 1787-1854.; Dwight family.; Dwight, Jonathan Edwards, 1759-1800?; Farnum, Lucretia Bancroft.; Gherardi, Jane Putnam Bancroft, 1798-1839.; Goodwin, D.; Louis Philippe, King of the French, 1773-1850.; Murphy, William.; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864.; Trowbridge, C. C.(Charles Christopher), 1800-1883.; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Witter, Baxter.; Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851.; Bank of Michigan.; Little, Brown and Company.; United States. President (1845-1849: Polk)
Subjects:
History, Modern--19th century.; Diplomacy.; Historiography.; History publishing.; Cabinet officers--United States.; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877).; Diplomatic and consular service, American.; Governors--Massachusetts.
Places:
United States--History--19th century.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; France--History--19th century.; France--History--Louis Philippe, 1830-1848.; France--Politics and government--19th century.; France--Politics and government--1830-1848.; Massachusetts--Politics and government--19th century.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a copy of the printed finding aid
- Correspondence 1803-1836 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1837-1841 (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1842-1848 (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1849-1855 (Box 4)
- Correspondence 1856-1866 (Box 5)
- Letter to Bancroft from John Bright1862 March 29 (Box 34, Folder 2)
- Correspondence 1867 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence 1868 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Correspondence 1869 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Correspondence 1870 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Correspondence 1871 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence 1872 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Correspondence 1873 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Correspondence 1874 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Correspondence 1875-1876 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Correspondence 1877-1879 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Correspondence 1880-1882 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Correspondence 1883-1887 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Correspondence concerning Robert Browning1887 (Box 34, Folder 1)
- Correspondence 1888-1901 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Correspondence Undated (Box 7, Folder 4-8)
- Genealogical Material (Box 7, Folder 9-14)
- "Library of the Late Honorable George Bancroft" (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Newspaper Clippings (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Printed Materials and Envelopes (Box 7, Folder 17)
- "7 Years in Berlin" (volume) (Box 8)
- Scrapbook with 1890 birthday telegrams and condolence messages on his death 1891 (Box 8)
- Volume with letters from Chancellor Ranke 1874-1875 (Box 8)
- Book notes (Box 9)
- Diplomas (Box 9)
- Photostats (Box 9)
- Photo album, Berlin 1874 (Box 10)
- Autograph book from "The Bluff," 1894-1899 (Box 10)
- Plaque from an Italian Academy (Box 10)
- Photo album, Berlin 1874 (Box 11)
  Includes folder containing photos of Victoria - Princess Royal and Prince Frederick Karl (Frederick III)
- Tribute to Bancroft in German [wooden box] (Box 12)
- Certificates from House of Reps., 1866 (Folder 1)
- Appointment of collector of customs for Boston, signed by Martin Van Buren, 1838 (Folder 1)
  Van Buren, Martin
- Additional papers (formerly in #2528)
- Correspondence 1885-1890, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Correspondence 1881-1883 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Correspondence 1862, 1867-1868, 1874-1875 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Robert Browning letter (original in Box 7, 1262) Sept. 30, 1887 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Bancroft documents 1851-1881 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- John C. Bancroft correspondence 1868-1869 n.d. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Louisa Denny Bancroft to John Chandler Bancroft 1864 1867-1870 1872 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Louisa Denny Bancroft to John Chandler Bancroft n.d. (Box 13, Folder 8)
- John Chandler and Louisa Denny Bancroft to children, friends, and relatives 1864 1873-1877 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Correspondence: Katherine Bott to Wilder D. Bancroft 1894-1895 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Correspondence: Katherine Bott to Wilder D. Bancroft n.d. (Box 13, Folder 11)